Inventory of the James Daniel Theberge Papers, 1963-1988
Hoover Institution Archives
James Daniel Theberge Papers,
1963-1988
88016
Hoover Institution Archives
52 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (22.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, dispatches, memoranda, reports, schedules, printed matter, and photographs, relating to diplomatic relations between the United States and Chile; political, social and economic conditions in Chile; United States foreign policy in Latin America; and communist movements in Latin America. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Number of Containers: 52 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box
Theberge, James Daniel
Access
Collection open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1988.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biographical/Historical Note
December 28, 1930 Born, New York
1961-1964 Economic advisor to U.S. embassy, Buenos Aires, Argentina
1963 Author, La Transformacion del capitalismo en el ciglo XX
1970-1975 Director of Latin American and Hispanic Studies Center, Georgetown University
1973 Author, Stability in the Caribbean
1975 Author, Russia in the Carribbean
1975-1977 U.S. ambassador to Nicaragua
1982-1985 U.S. ambassador to Chile
January 20, 1988 Died, Montego Bay, Jamaica
Source: "James Daniel Theberge." Contemporary Authors Online. Detroit: Gale, 2000.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers relate to diplomatic relations between the United States and Chile; political, social and economic conditions in Chile; United States foreign policy in Latin America; and communist movements in Latin America. They are comprised of correspondence, speeches and writings, dispatches, memoranda, reports, schedules, printed matter, and photographs.
Reagan, Ronald.; United States. Department of State.; Chile--Economic conditions--1973-1988.; Chile--Foreign relations--United States.; Chile--Politics and government--1973-1988.; Chile.; Communism--Latin America.; Communism.; Diplomats--United States.; Latin America--Foreign relations--United States.; Latin America.; United States--Foreign relations--Chile.; United States--Foreign relations--Latin America.; United States--Foreign relations.
- Speeches and writings (Box 1-5)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes related notes and research materials
  - "U.S. and Latin America in the World System,", 1978-1983 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - "Latin America, U.S. and the West: A View from Washington,", 1975-1982 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Published articles and speech materials, 1978-1985 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - "The History and Organization of the U.S. Department of State" (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Commonsense: A Republican Journal of Thought and Opinion, Volume 3, Number 2, 1980 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - La Transformacion del capitalismo en el siglo XX, undated (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - "The Defense of American Democracy,", July 1984 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - General
    - Directory of the Rotary Club of Santiago, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Printed material on Latin America, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - Embassy of the United States in Chile seminar, "The Information Age,", August 1984 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Chile, 1987 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Soviet policy, 1987 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Chile, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Chile. Theberge analyses and project, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Latin America-Soviet Union miscellaneous notes, 1987 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - International newspaper clippings, 1985 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Latin America miscellaneous notes, 1987 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Theberge speech on U.S./Soviet Union/Cuba Triangle, Georgetown University, 30 November 1972 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - "Spain After Carrerro Blanco," draft, June 1973 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - International Institute for Strategic Studies speech on the Soviet Union in the Caribbean, 17 April 1972 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Letters to the editor, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Monthly Senate Luncheon seminar, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - "The Case Against the Naive Application of Rate of Return Analysis to Eeducation Project Evaluation in Developing Countries" (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Monthly Senate Luncheon seminars, Western Hemisphere, 15 August 1974 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Informal discussion on raw materials, 18 June 1974 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Monthly senate luncheon seminar, Panama Canal Treaty Negotiations, 6 June 1974 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Congressional Seminar, Raw Materials in the Western Hemisphere, 27 March 1974 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Kenyon Public Affairs Forum, 25-28 April 1974 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Chile, Movimiento Democrático Popular-Partido Comunista de Chile-LED (MDP-PCCH-LED) democratic popular movement, 1984 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Brazil versus United States, undated (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - "Granma Editorial: A Reply,", undated (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - Senate Finance Committee Luncheon Seminar on Cuban foreign policy, 21 May 1975 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - U.S. Relations with Canada and Mexico, 25-27 April 1974 (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - Chile Congressional Seminar, 15 August 1974 (Box-folder 3: 17)
  - Chile, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - Congressional statements on Chile, 1973 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - Chile Testimony, House Subcommittee on Inter-American Affairs, September 1974 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Chile. Economic chapter, 1986 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Latin American policy, 1974-1985 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Speeches, 1982-1985 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - U.S. policy towards Chile, 1987 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Latin America research financing correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - "The Doorstep Challenge,", March 1981 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Terrorism network in Chile, undated (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - "Eight Blocks that Rule Chile/Santiago,", undated (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Latin American Conservative Party International founding document, 1986 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Alternativa, Issue 1, Number 1, April 1986 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - "Mi punto de vista," Vision article, 21 October 1974 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Statement before the Joint Economic Committee on cartels, 22 July 1974 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - U.S. Army War College briefing on the Soviet Union in Latin America, 30 April 1974 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - U.S. Army War College briefing, Carlisle, Pennsylvania, 30 April 1974 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Spanish language journals, October 1974 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Book review, 1972-1976 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Latin American book review list, October 1974 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Russia in the Caribbean, book promotion and book reviews, undated (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Stability in the Caribbean, book promotion and book reviews, undated (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Valley Forge conferences on Latin America, Summer 1974 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Conference on Soviet and Chinese Influence in the Third World, Philadelphia, 25-26 October 1973 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Westinghouse Briefing, Pittsburgh, 31 October 1974 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - TV Channel V (Panorama), James D. Theberge discusses Portugal politics, 7 April 1975 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - Department of State briefing, Ambassador to Madrid, Spain, 21 February 1975 (Box-folder 5: 15)
  - Soviet Naval Conference, 8-11 September 1974 (Box-folder 5: 16)
  - Latin America Development Administration Committee, Washington seminar, 1974 (Box-folder 5: 17)
  - Peruvian War College briefing, 16 September 1972 (Box-folder 5: 18)
  - Soviet military activity briefing, Center for Strategic and International Studies (CSIS), November 1970 (Box-folder 5: 19)
  - Briefing for Ralph Pfeiffer, IBM Americas and Asia, April 1974 (Box-folder 5: 20)
  - "Spanish Commercial Policy in North Africa," article, September 1972 (Box-folder 5: 21)
  - "A Brief Review of Aid Program Loans to Latin America," article, 7 December 1966 (Box-folder 5: 22)
  - "Spanish Industrial Development Policy in the 20th Century,", July 1975 (Box-folder 5: 23)
  - "A Soviet View of Détente, Implications for American Foreign Policy," article, 26 February 1974 (Box-folder 5: 24)
  - "Foreign Trade Act Reveals Difficulties of Kissinger's New Dialogue with Latin America,", 19 February 1975 (Box-folder 5: 25)
  - Peruvian War College briefing, 17 October 1974 (Box-folder 5: 26)
  - Testimony before Senate Appropriations Committee, 13 December 1974 (Box-folder 5: 27)
  - Latin American briefing for Ralph Pfeiffer, IBM World Trade Corporation, 10 May 1975 (Box-folder 5: 28)
- Subject file
  - Chile, action items, 1982 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Embassy appointments, July 1985 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - Senator Ibanez congressional luncheon, 21 May 1974 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Writings and materials regarding Chile, 1973-1987 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - Clippings on Chile, 1987 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - Chile, 1986 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Foreign policy, Chile, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Foreign policy, Latin America, 1967-1971 (Box-folder 6: 8)
- Printed matter, 1969
  - America Armed: Essays on United States Military Policy, 1969 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Cosas, una revista internacional, Numbers 272 and 275, 5 March 1987, 9 April 1987 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - Atlas, regionalizado de Chile, 1981 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Atlas geografico de Chile para la educacion, 1985 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - Supresion por el comunismo de la prensa opositora and comunicacion y lucha ideologica, 1976 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - Hoy, La verdad sin compromisos, Number 496, 19 January 1987 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Cuentas nacionales de Chile 1960-1980 (Box-folder 6: 7)
- Subject file
  - Post-Pinochet Chile, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - U.S. policy towards Chile, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - Chile, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - Politics in Chile, 1983 (Box-folder 7: 4-5)
  - Seleccion de Textos, del Archivo de la Presidencia de la Republica (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - Chile, 1985 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - American foreign relations, 1985 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Inter-American Businessmen's Association Speech, Miami, Florida, undated (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Gonzalo Vial. "Decline, Consensus and National Unity in 1973" (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - Clase Obrera y Modelo Economico, 1983 (Box-folder 8: 5)
- Correspondence (Box-folder 9-11)
  - August-December 1982 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - January-May 1983 (Box-folder 9: 2)
  - June-December 1983 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - January-June 1984 (Box-folder 10: 2)
  - July-December 1984 (Box-folder 11: 1)
  - 1985 (Box-folder 11: 2)
- Daily schedule (incomplete), 1983-1987 (Box-folder 12: 1)
- Schedules, 1982-1984 (Box-folder 12: 2)
- Daily schedules, 1985 (Box-folder 12: 3)
- Chronological files (Box-folder 13-24)
  Includes notes, draft writings, collected articles, and other materials mainly on Chile and Chilean politics.
  - 1982 (Box-folder 13: 1)
  - 1973-1985 (Box-folder 13: 2)
  - 1982-1985 (Box-folder 13: 3)
  - January-August 1982 (Box-folder 14: 1)
  - September-December 1982 (Box-folder 14: 2)
  - January-June 1982 (Box-folder 14: 3)
  - July-December 1982 (Box-folder 14: 4)
  - 1982-1985 (Box-folder 15: 1)
  - 1982-1983 (Box-folder 15: 2)
  - April-July 1983 (Box-folder 15: 3)
  - 1982-1983 (Box-folder 15: 4)
  - 1982-1985 (Box-folder 16: 1-2)
  - January-March 1983 (Box-folder 17: 1)
  - April-August 1983 (Box-folder 17: 2)
  - September-December 1983 (Box-folder 17: 3)
  - 1983 Annex (Box-folder 17: 4)
  - January-June 1984 (Box-folder 18: 1)
  - October-December 1983 (Box-folder 18: 2)
  - August-September 1983 (Box-folder 18: 3)
  - 1984-1985 (Box-folder 18: 4)
  - December 1983-January 1984 (Box-folder 19: 1)
  - February-June 1984 (Box-folder 19: 2)
  - January-March 1984 (Box-folder 19: 3)
  - March-April 1984 (Box-folder 19: 4)
  - May-July 1984 (Box-folder 19: 5)
  - July-September 1984 (Box-folder 20: 1)
  - September 1984 (Box-folder 20: 2)
  - October-November 1984 (Box-folder 20: 3)
  - September-December 1984 (Box-folder 21: 1-3)
  - 1984-1985 (Box-folder 22: 1-2)
  - October-December 1984 (Box-folder 22: 3)
  - September 1984-June 1985 (Box-folder 23: 1)
  - 1985 (Box-folder 23: 2)
  - March-June 1985 (Box-folder 24: 1)
  - January-March 1985 (Box-folder 24: 2)
- Biographies of military leaders, 1985 (Box-folder 24: 3)
- Chronological files (Box-folder 25-26)
  - April-June 1985 (Box-folder 25: 1)
  - May-June 1985 (Box-folder 25: 2)
  - June-July 1985 (Box-folder 25: 3)
  - June-July 1985 (Contd.) (Box-folder 26: 1)
  - August-December 1985 (Box-folder 26: 2)
- Press material (Box-folder 27-31)
  - March-April 1983 (Box-folder 27: 1-2)
  - May-June 1983 (Box-folder 27: 3-4)
  - July 1983 (Box-folder 28: 1-2)
  - August 1983 (Box-folder 28: 3)
  - September 1983 (Box-folder 29: 1)
  - September 1983 (Box-folder 29: 2)
  - November 1983 (Box-folder 30: 1)
  - March-May 1985 (Box-folder 30: 2)
  - March-May 1985 (Contd.) (Box-folder 31: 1-2)
- Photographs (Box-folder 31-33)
  - Early 1982 (Box-folder 31: 3-4)
  - 1985 (Box-folder 32: 1-3)
  - Appointment, etc., 1979-1982 (Box-folder 33: 1-2)
  - Arrival in Chile, 1982 (Box-folder 33: 1-2)
- U.S. newspaper clippings (Box-folder 34-35)
  - January-February 1984 (Box-folder 34: 1-2)
  - December 1983 (Box-folder 34: 3)
  - October-November 1984 (Box-folder 35: 1)
  - December 1984-February 1985 (Box-folder 35: 2)
  - February-March 1985 (Box-folder 35: 3)
- Newspaper clippings on Chile (Box-folder 36-42)
  - March-April 1983 (Box-folder 36: 1)
  - Ambassador's clippings file, August-December 1983 (Box-folder 36: 2-3)
  - December 1983 (Box-folder 37: 1)
  - January 1984 (Box-folder 37: 2)
  - January-February 1984 (Box-folder 37: 3)
  - March-April 1984 (Box-folder 37: 4)
  - May-June 1984 (Box-folder 38: 1)
  - July-September 1984 (Box-folder 38: 2-3)
  - October-November 1984 (Box-folder 39: 1)
  - December 1984-March 1985 (Box-folder 39: 2)
  - Ambassador's clippings file, January-March 1985 (Box-folder 39: 3)
  - April-June 1985 (Box-folder 40: 1)
  - July 1985 (Box-folder 40: 2-3)
  - July-December 1986 (Box-folder 41: 1)
  - Barnes at Rojas funeral, 8 July 1986 (Box-folder 41: 2)
  - Jorge Edwards, Theberge, Barnes article, 13 July 1986 (Box-folder 41: 3)
  - Abrams policy towards Chile, 20 July 1986 (Box-folder 41: 4)
  - University elections/politics, April-December 1986 (Box-folder 41: 5)
  - January-June 1986 (Box-folder 41: 6)
  - June 1986 (Box-folder 41: 7)
  - 1986-1987 (Box-folder 41: 8)
  - March 1987 (Box-folder 41: 9)
  - February 1987 (Box-folder 41: 10)
  - January 1987 (Box-folder 41: 11)
  - Ariel Dorfman, New York Times Magazine, June 1986 (Box-folder 42: 1)
  - U.S. policy regarding friendly despots, April 1986 (Box-folder 42: 2)
  - April 1987 (Box-folder 42: 3)
  - May 1987 (Box-folder 42: 4)
  - September 1987 (Box-folder 42: 5)
  - August 1987 (Box-folder 42: 6)
  - July 1987 (Box-folder 42: 7)
  - June 1987 (Box-folder 42: 8)
- Chile subject file (Box-folder 43-52)
  - Foreign Press/Pinochet Regime (Nixon), 1986-1987 (Box-folder 43: 1)
  - Amnesty International (R. Grenier), 1986 (Box-folder 43: 2)
  - Latin American Monitor, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 43: 3)
  - Analysis of 1980/1925 Constitutions: F. Bulnes, 1986 (Box-folder 43: 4)
  - Opinion polls, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 43: 5)
  - Geopolitical interests in southern cone, November 1986 (Box-folder 43: 6)
  - Arms industry, August 1986 (Box-folder 43: 7)
  - Latin American School of Social Science (FLACSO) history, 1980-1987 (Box-folder 43: 8)
  - U.S. involvement in military coup of 1973, 1975-1986 (Box-folder 43: 9)
  - Domestic politics, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 43: 10)
  - Union Nacional party publications, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 43: 11)
  - Augusto Pinochet, 1973 (Box-folder 43: 12)
  - Pinochet's vision of Marxism, 1986 (Box-folder 43: 13)
  - National Accord, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 43: 14)
  - Régis Debray. The Chilean Revolution: Conversations with Allende, undated (Box-folder 43: 15)
  - Liberation theology, Christian-Marxist dialogue, 1986 (Box-folder 44: 1)
  - Catholic Church. Radicalization process in Latin America, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 44: 2)
  - Paper on the "Lessons of Chile Learned by USSR,", 1974 (Box-folder 44: 3)
  - Soviet diplomatic representation worldwide, June 1987 (Box-folder 44: 4)
  - Georgraphy, 1963 (Box-folder 44: 5)
  - Latin debt/economy, Chilean economy, long-term growth, 1980-1987 (Box-folder 44: 6)
  - Terrorism, Partido Comunista de Chile/Manuel Rodríguez Patriotic Front (PCCH/MRPF) arms caches, August 1986 (Box-folder 44: 7)
  - U.S. policy, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 44: 8)
  - Christian Left, 1983 (Box-folder 44: 9)
  - Patterns of change. Bureaucratic/authoritarian state, 1976 (Box-folder 44: 10)
  - Gabriel Valdes speeches, 1986 (Box-folder 44: 11)
  - Renovación Nacional, 1987 (Box-folder 44: 12)
  - Political opening, party positions, December 1983 (Box-folder 44: 13)
  - Economy. Debt negotiations, January-April 1983 (Box-folder 44: 14)
  - Renato Hevia, December 1985 (Box-folder 45: 1)
  - Christian Right, December 1985 (Box-folder 45: 2)
  - National transition, 1985 (Box-folder 45: 3)
  - Church opposition and church activities, 1985 (Box-folder 45: 4)
  - Juan Francisco Fresno (Cardinal), 1985 (Box-folder 45: 5)
  - Democratic transition, National Accords, 1985 (Box-folder 45: 6)
  - Benavente, political analyses, June 1984-July 1985 (Box-folder 46: 1)
  - Easter Island trip, January 1983 (Box-folder 46: 2)
  - Pacific Basin Economic Conference, 1983 (Box-folder 47: 1)
  - Economy, 1984 (Box-folder 47: 2)
  - Chilean foreign policy documents, 1984 (Box-folder 48: 1)
  - Regional (Zappalar) history, April 1983 (Box-folder 48: 2)
  - Collected papers, 1976-1983 (Box-folder 48: 3)
  - U.S.-Chilean relations, historical survey, 1981 (Box-folder 48: 4)
  - Soviet articles on Latin America, 1984 (Box-folder 48: 5)
  - Antarctic trip, February 1984 (Box-folder 49: 1)
  - Assorted documents and articles, 1984 (Box-folder 49: 2)
  - Privatization, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 49: 3)
  - Easter Island essays, 1984 (Box-folder 49: 4)
  - Press coverage of Nestor D. Sanchez visit to Santiago, Chile, March 1985 (Box-folder 50: 1)
  - L.C. Faron, Hawks of the Sun: Mapuche Morality and Its Regional Attributes, 1964 (Box-folder 50: 2)
  - Projects, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 50: 3)
  - Central American briefing book, undated (Box-folder 50: 4)
  - Antarctic trip, March 1983 (Box-folder 50: 5)
  - Anglo-Argentine War, 1982 (Box-folder 50: 6)
  - Political instability in Chile, 1986 (Box-folder 51: 1)
  - Chile, 1986 (Box-folder 51: 2)
  - Military, 1973-1986 (Box-folder 51: 3)
  - Post-transition material, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 51: 4)
  - Map of Managua, Nicaragua (Box-folder 51: 5)
  - Hitos de la liberacion, 11 September 1973 (Box-folder 51)
  - Leonard J. Theberge memorial service, October 1983 (Box-folder 52: 1)
  - Chilean news coverage of protests and responses, May 1983 (Box-folder 52: 2)
  - Chile, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 52: 3)
- Biografia de S. E. El Presidente de la Republica de Chile e Integrantes de la Honorable Junta de Gobierno, 1985 (Box-folder 52: 4)
- Photograph album (Box-folder 52: 5)
- Decorative seal (Box-folder 53)
- Commemorative tray (Box-folder 53)
- Declassified U.S. government records, 1980-1985
  - 2018 release of declassified records, 1980-1985 (Reading room workstation)